We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s time for the
Nutrition Facts Grab Bag
where we look at the science
on a whole variety of topics.
Today, we start with
an unusual finding.
Did you know that
burning incense
has been found to generate
about four times
the particulate matter
as burning cigarettes?
Here’s the story.
Frankincense and myrrh date
back to thousands of years
before the three wise men.
The burning of witch's incense
may have actually had
a hygienic functions,
like maybe repelling mosquitoes,
and when put to the test,
incense fumes were able to kill off
some bacteria and mold in the air
but may also carry health risks.
Although the adverse health effects
of second-hand tobacco smoke
are well recognized, the impact
of burning incense in the home
has received less attention, but
burning incense has been found
to generate like four times the
particulate matter as cigarettes;
so, incense may be even worse!
No wonder home incense use
may have significant adverse
health effects, particularly
on the heart and lungs,
including childhood asthma.
No wonder, since the incense
smoke particle size
peaks down in the danger range,
so ultrafine they can float
down into the deepest
parts of the lungs.
It’s not just the little ash
particles in the smoke though,
there’s carbon monoxide, nitric
oxides, sulfur dioxide,
carcinogenic polycyclic
aromatic hydrocarbons,
and volatile organic compounds
like benzene and formaldehyde.
The World Health Organization suggests
limiting indoor formaldehyde
to about 80 parts per billion,
but even with a window open
during the hour or so
incense is burning,
formaldehyde levels
exceed the safety limit.
What does this all mean in
terms of disease outcomes?
Studies on rats show incense can
do all sorts of terrible things,
but what about people?
A study of thousands of children
followed over time found
that exposure to household
incense burning was associated
with impaired lung function,
reduced lung function growth,
and increased risks of
respiratory diseases and symptoms.
Daily exposure is associated
with impaired lung function
in adolescents too, though
interestingly those who had
pets at home appeared to
have better lung function.
Something I noted previously, how
having a dog or cat in the house
during early life may protect against
childhood asthma and allergy.
What about the heart?
Long-term exposure to incense
burning in the home environment
was associated with an increased
risk of cardiovascular mortality.
Approximately 8 percent of
heart disease deaths and
12 percent of stroke deaths could
potentially be attributed
to incense use, though they were
looking at long-term exposure,
so like incense burning at home on
a daily basis for more than 20 years.
What about cancer?
Temple workers exposed to incense
day in and day out were found
to have evidence of
signiﬁcantly more DNA damage,
including DNA strand breaks.
Does this translate
into greater cancer risk?
One unsolved mystery has been
why non-smoking Asian women
have such high lung cancer rates.
Might it be incense?
Probably not, since the
association between incense use
and lung cancer
remains inconclusive,
though incense use does
appear to be linked to cancers
of the upper respiratory tract,
as well as brain tumors
among children whose mother
were exposed to incense.
Three times the odds, even more
than that of second-hand smoke.
In fact, even more than the
consumption of bologna sandwiches.
Processed meat consumption
only appears to at most
double brain tumor
risk among children.
Even without tumors, a study of
15,000 infants found that
household incense burning
was associated with a delay
in brain development milestones
such as when they start to walk.
And then on the other
side of the life cycle,
incense exposure among older adults
was associated with reduced
cognitive performance and adverse
structural changes in the brain.
The researchers conclude that
this calls for safer practices,
such as avoiding
burning incense indoors
or using safer incense alternatives.
So-called environmentally friendly
types of incense have been
put to the test, and…
they were found to contain
even higher concentrations
of several potentially carcinogenic
polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons.
Despite being a
recognized health hazard,
burning incense remains
in widespread use.
In the very least, we may want to
avoid burning incense in the home
when susceptible
individuals are present,
such as the very young,
the very old, or
people with a family history of
allergy or pre-existing
cardiovascular or respiratory disease.
One innovative suggestion
is electronic incense,
like the e-cigarette
of the incense world,
so you can get the fragrance
without the combustion
by-products of smoke.
Most of the concern about
e-cigarette-related adverse events
traditionally have revolved
around the nicotine,
which wouldn’t be a
problem with e-incense,
the concern that e-cigarette use
would lead to real cigarette use.
But now that there have been
thousands of cases of lung injury
associated with vaping, and
we’re still actually not sure
what’s causing the issue,
it seems to me we
should figure that out
before we push for the
electronic incense equivalent.
One option in the meantime
is scented candles,
which, under normal
conditions of use,
do not appear to pose known
health risks to the consumer.
Next up, we look
at specific foods
that have shown in
randomized controlled trials
to improve symptoms
like hot flashes.
There is a great
variety of symptoms
suffered by women
undergoing menopause.
There are the so-called
vasomotor symptoms,
like night sweats and hot
ﬂashes, diﬃculty sleeping
or full-on insomnia, vaginal
dryness, and pain during sex,
as well as adverse effects on mood
including full-blown depression.
Might exercise help?
Exercise can certainly help with
physical and psychological quality
of life in general, but unfortunately
there was no evidence
for the eﬀects of exercise on
menopause-speciﬁc symptoms.
You know researchers are
getting desperate when they try
to see if giving people
pig placenta will help.
Spoiler alert: it doesn’t.
Well, we know oxidative stress,
which is a consequence of
excessive free oxygen radicals
or impaired antioxidant defense,
is linked not only to diseases
such as diabetes, obesity,
and cardiovascular disease,
but also menopausal
symptoms like hot flashes.
Low free oxygen radical
defense is associated with
more menopausal symptoms,
just like having a diet with more
antioxidants is associated
with fewer menopausal symptoms.
In fact, a high intake of
fruits and vegetables may delay
the onset of menopause
in the first place,
thought to be because
the presence of antioxidants
in fruits and vegetables may
counteract the adverse effects
of free radicals on the number
of functional eggs you still have
in your ovaries, whereas
a reason high meat consumption
has been related to
degenerative diseases
may not just be the
saturated fat and cholesterol,
but the pro-oxidation products
generated during their production,
storage, digestion,
and metabolism of meat.
Similarly, since a pro-
inflammatory diet has also been
associated with higher menopause-
specific somatic symptoms,
meaning like hot flashes
and sleep issues,
that would mean moving
towards a more plant-based diet
packed with anti-inflammatory
components like fiber
and away from pro-inflammatory
foods containing
saturated fat and cholesterol.
No wonder whole plant
foods intake has been
associated with fewer
menopausal symptoms.
In terms of specific foods,
poultry and skim dairy products
may be particularly bad,
whereas soy milk seemed to help.
So, women may derive benefit
from lower consumption
of poultry and skimmed dairy
and a greater consumption
of vegetables and soy milk.
You don’t really know, though...
until you put it to the test.
And indeed, women randomized
to drink soy milk reduced
their menopausal symptoms by
20 percent within 12 weeks.
No wonder that those eating
strictly plant-based diets
report less bothersome
menopausal symptoms.
Among women undergoing menopause,
vegans reported less
bothersome symptoms,
and within the diet
groups more vegetables,
and in the meat-eating group,
less ﬂesh food was associated
with less bothersome
symptoms as well.
So, eating a plant-based
diet may be helpful for women
in their menopausal transition
who prefer a natural means
to manage their symptoms,
consistent with all the other
studies demonstrating reduced
menopausal symptoms in those
consuming greater quantities of
plant-based foods and less meat.
But again, maybe
there are other reasons
healthier eaters
have fewer symptoms.
You can’t prove cause and
effect until...you guessed it.
An interventional trial to
see if changing your diet
actually reduces symptoms.
And in this study, where women
were encouraged to decrease fat
and increase fruit, vegetable,
and whole grain intake,
they were significantly
more likely to eliminate
their vasomotor symptoms like
hot flashes and night sweats
compared to the control group.
So, it’s certainly not all or nothing.
And within a plant-based
diet, those randomized
to a meat-free diet with
daily flaxseed oil, walnuts,
and almonds did better
than those randomized
to the same diet but with
daily extra-virgin olive oil.
After 16 weeks, the
vegetarian diet that was rich
in omega-3s did better reducing
vasomotor symptom frequency.
In fact, even just two teaspoons
worth of ground flaxseeds a day
alone can significantly decrease
menopausal symptoms to about
the same extent as
hormone replacement therapy,
but without the side effects.
Finally today,
we have more info
on that fabulous spice fenugreek
and how it can help control blood sugar.
The spice fenugreek is
considered to be one of
humanity’s oldest medicinal plants.
What can it do?
In my last video on fenugreek,
I explored the evidence showing
it can improve sexual
function in both men and women,
decrease menstrual pain,
and boost milk production
in lactating mothers.
And what are the side effects?
Fifteen randomized controlled
trials show, on average,
a significant improvement
in cholesterol levels.
And a dozen other studies show
significant improvements
in both long- and short-term blood
sugar control in diabetics
and prediabetics using an average of
about a half teaspoon a day
over a period of an
average of two months.
Results clearly indicate that
fenugreek is an inexpensive,
low-risk dietary supplement
that has potential
to improve blood sugar
control in diabetes.
What exactly is the mechanism by
which it lowers blood sugars?
There’s a peculiar amino
acid in fenugreek
that increases insulin
release from the pancreas.
The peculiar 4-hydroxyisoleucine
has been described as
an efﬁcient compound in the
regulation of insulin secretion.
Due to the fact that it
acts as a secretagogue
in the presence of elevated
blood glucose concentrations,
it has been proposed for
the potential treatment
of insulin resistance,
diabetes, and obesity.
There’s a class of diabetes drugs
that does the same thing:
sulfonylureas, sold as like glucotrol,
glyburide, micronase, glipizide.
The problem is that they
increase insulin secretion
whether you need it or not,
and so there’s a risk
of severe hypoglycemia,
driving your blood sugars too low.
The funky fenugreek amino
acid, on the other hand,
only boosts it when you need it.
When your blood sugars are
normal, it has no effect.
It only seems to stimulate
extra insulin release
when you need it most, when
your blood sugars are high.
What these researchers did,
was after consent was obtained
from family members,
pancreases were obtained
from brain-dead organ donors.
Put the insulin-secreting
cells in a petri dish
at a low blood sugar concentration,
and they release a little insulin,
and at high blood sugar levels
they release more insulin.
That makes sense.
That’s what they’re supposed to do,
since insulin is the
hormone your body releases
when trying to bring
down your blood sugars.
Add in some of that
fenugreek amino acid, though,
and you can boost insulin
production. Great!
But if that happened even at the
low blood sugar concentration too,
it would be like the drugs
and you could dip too low,
but no, when you don’t need extra
insulin, no fenugreek effect.
What about the role of fenugreek
in the prevention of type 2 diabetes?
A 3-year randomized controlled
study of the efficacy
of fenugreek on men and women
diagnosed with prediabetes.
Those randomized to fenugreek
were told to take about
one and a third teaspoons of
fenugreek powder twice a day
before meals, and both the fenugreek
and the control groups that
didn’t get any fenugreek
were both given identical
diet and lifestyle advice.
And, by the end of the study,
the cumulative incidence rate
of diabetes was reduced significantly
in the fenugreek group.
Check it out. Those who didn’t
get the fenugreek
had a four times higher
chance of developing diabetes,
and you could already see
the groups starting to diverge
within six months, and all
from just a few cents worth
of a spice, every day.
If you yourself want to
intimately support this kind of
amazing research in the future,
be sure to register
at organdonor.gov.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it
on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you
need –
plus, links to all
of
the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.